# 大家好 前幾天我在這裡種甘蔗哦
Hi everyone. We've planted some sugar canes here a couple of days ago.
# 看一下有沒有發芽
Let's see if they have started sprouting.
# 上次因為種的比較急 (註︰以我所知這裡的急不是急著種完，而是事件沒太多準備)
We didn't film it last time,
# 沒拍視頻
as we didn't have the time.
# 這次我特地過來 把它挖起來看一下
That's why I'm coming again, to dig it up and have a look.
# 不知道會不會發芽
Let's see if there are any sprouts.
# 這個
This one...
# 出來啦
It's coming out.
# 你看
Look!
# 快發芽啦 看見沒有 這些都是
It'll be sprouting soon. See? There are all,
# 青的 它這個長 長那個莖的
all green. The, the stems will be coming up here.
# 這裡可以就看得出來
I can tell by simply looking at it.
# 你看 這邊
Look! This side,
# 這邊 這個看一下
this side. Let me have a look.
# 你看 這裡 這裡有青色的哦 看到沒有
Look! Here, here is a green spot. See?
# 這就準備發芽啦
That means it's ready to sprout.
# 你看 這個芽
Look! The sprout,
# 都露出了一點點哦
a bit of it is already coming out.
# 把它包回去
I'll wrap it up again.
# 把它種下去又把它挖起來
I shouldn't dig it up right after planting it.
# 哎呀 不好意思啊
Aya! My apologies.
# 這個芽 這個芽馬上出來啦
This sprout, this sprout will be coming out very soon.
# 一點點
A tiny little bit
# 啊 這裡
Ah! Here
# 這個芽那麼大啦
This sprout is already that big.
# 馬上就會長出來啦
It will be coming out very soon.
# 種下去才五六天左右
They were planted just five or six days ago.
# 也不是很久
It's not a long time.
# 把它埋回去
Let me put it back.
# 到時候 明年的春天就有甘蔗吃啦
Then, we can have sugar canes in the spring next year.
# 就不用去拿兄弟家的啦
We don't need to take from our buddy any more.
# 上次拿兄弟家的
Last time, when I took my buddy's sugar canes,
# 說好了是拿一根一根
I promised to take one, just one.
# 我拿了十幾二十根回來
But I came back with a dozen.
# 今年他甘蔗都每[SIC]種
He didn't plant any sugar canes this year.
# 田都荒在那裡 他不種啦
The field is just over there, abandoned.
# 不知道幹嘛
Who knows what happened to him.
# 看他甘蔗賣得也挺好的啊
The sales of his sugar canes are rather good, in fact.
# 好啦 反正這應該也長得出二三十棵
Anyway, here I think I'll have a dozen or two,
# 甘蔗出來
of sugar canes.
# 夠我吃的啦
It's well enough for me.
# 這裡 這裡搞一個 一整條都有
Here, I put one here. And it grows all along this row.
# 那邊還有一行
And there's one more row.
# 都是
The same.
# 你看
Look!
# 我們種的大蒜
This is our garlic.
# 你看 我在這土里面還種了大蒜哦
Look! I've also planted some garlic here.
# 你看 這個大蒜
Look at this garlic.
# 很靚的吧
It's beautiful, isn't it?
# 前 前五六天 跟甘蔗一起種下去的 你看
I planted them with the sugar canes five, five or six days ago.
# 現在那麼多啦
There are so many now.
# 這個大蒜很快的 它長了那麼高 我就把它拔啦
The garlic grows very fast. I'll pick them up when they're about that tall.
# 把它拿去賣呀
Then we can sell them.
# 你看 這一片 那邊還有
Look! The whole area here, and there too.
# 這一片都是我家的
This whole area here is my,
# 那個
I mean,
# 菜園
veggie garden.
# 那邊有青菜呀
There are some veggies,
# 蘿蔔呀
radish.
# 這邊我全部用來種了這個大蒜
But I reserve here for the garlic.
# 你看 這個蒜苗幾乎都是百分之一百成活的哦
The survival rate of the sprouts here is almost always a hundred percent.
# 沒有
There are no,
# 沒有 沒有假的 全是真的 (註︰怎麼假的大蒜，想說甚麼？)
no, no fake ones. All are real and genuine.
# 長得好快呀
They grow really fast.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個草木灰 我把草木灰放下去肥下它們
This is wood ash. I put some wood ash here as fertilizer.
# 它們長得好快
And they grow really fast.
# 你看
Look!
# 烏黑發亮哦
It's shining black.
# 再過一個月的話 應該就可以拔蒜苗賣
I think they can be picked for sale after a month.
# 來這菜園里面
We're now in the veggie garden.
# 搞點這個 這個菜花呀
Let me pick some, some veggies,
# 菜花給攝影小哥帶回去
veggies for Mr. Cameraman.
# 這個是 綠色無公害的哦
These are, organic vegetables,
# 沒有施 沒有施過化肥的
without, without any chemical fertilizers.
# 它這菜就很[好]種的
Growing these vegetables doesn't need too much effort.
# 種下去就不用管
Plant it, leave it growing, that's it.
# 每天 每天都有很拗
Then we can,
# 每天 每天都有得拗
come here, come here and pick some everyday.
# 我都拗了好多啦
I've already picked a lot.
# 很多鄰居都 他們沒種菜的都到我這邊來拗
Many neighbours also come here and pick some if they don't grow any veggies at home.
# 我叫他隨便拗
I ask them to take whatever they like.
# 不用給我客氣
It's my pleasure.
# 夠啦
It's enough.
# 這裡夠吃一兩餐啦
It's enough for a meal or two.
# 到時候吃完 吃完再拔
We can pick again, when it's finished.
# 再進來
We can come again,
# 再進來拗
and pick more.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 我要回家煮飯啦
I need to go back home and cook.